This is very strange for me, because I’m not used to doing this:
إنه لأمر غريب بالنسبة لي، لأنني غير معتاد على القيام بذلك
I usually stand on the other side of the light,
أنا أقف عادة خلف الأضواء
and now I'm feeling the pressure I put other people into. And it's hard ...
وأشعر الآن بالضغط الذي أفرضه على الناس، وهذا أمر صعب
The previous speaker has, I think,
أعتقد أن المتحدث السابق قد
really painted a very good background as to
رسم حقيقة خلفية جيدة جداً عن ما هو
the impulse behind my work and what drives me, and my sense of loss,
الدافع الحقيقي وراء عملي وما يقودني، وعن إحساسي بالخسارة
and trying to find the answer to the big questions.
وعن محاولتي إيجاد إجابة للأسئلة المهمة
But this, for me, I mean, coming here to do this,
لكن هذا الأمر، بالنسبة لي، القدوم إلى هنا لفعل ذلك، أشعر مثل،
feels like -- there’s this sculptor that I like very much, Giacometti,
أشعر مثل، هناك نحات أحبه كثيراً هو جياكوميتي
who after many years of living in France -- and learning, you know,
الذي بعد سنوات من العيش في فرنسا، والتعلم، تعلمون
studying and working -- he returned home and he was asked, what did you produce?
العمل والدراسة، عاد إلى الوطن وسئل، ما الذي أنتجته؟
What have you done with so many years of being away?
ماذا فعلت خلال هذه السنوات العديدة من بقائك بعيداً عن الوطن؟
And he sort of, he showed a handful of figurines.
ونوعاً ما، عرض حفنة من التماثيل الصغيرة
And obviously they were, "Is this what you spent years doing?
وقد تفاجئوا قائلين " هل هذا ما أمضيت سنوات تقوم به؟
And we expected huge masterpieces!"
وتوقعنا، تعلمون، روائع فنية ضخمة، تعلمون..."
But what struck me is the understanding that in those little pieces
لكن ما صدمني هو معرفة أنه في هذه القطع الصغيرة
was the culmination of a man’s life, search, thought, everything --
كان ذروة بحث الرجل عن الحياة، وفكره وكل شيء
just in a reduced, small version.
فقط بنسخة موجزة وصغيرة.
In a way, I feel like that.
بطريقة ما، أنا أشعر بمثل ذلك.
I feel like I’m coming home to talk about
أشعر وكأنني عائد إلى الوطن لأتكلم عن
what I’ve been away doing for 20 years.
ما كنت أفعله بعيداً عن الوطن لمدة عشرين سنة الآن.
And I will start with a brief taster of what I’ve been about:
وسأبدأ بلمحة موجزة عن ما فعلته.
a handful of films -- nothing much,
حفنة من الأفلام، لا شيئ أكثر من -
two feature films and a handful of short films.
فيلمين رئيسين والقليل من الأفلام القصيرة.
So, we’ll go with the first piece.
هكذا، سنذهب مع الجزء الأول.
(Video) Woman: "I destroy lives," mum said.
فيديو: أنا أدمر حياة الأخرين، أمي قالت ذلك.
I love her, you know.
أحبها، تعلم.
She’s not even my real mum.
هي حتى ليست أمي الحقيقية.
My real mum and dad dumped me
أمي وأبي الحقيقيان تخليا عني
and fucked off back to Nigeria.
واللعينان عادا إلى نيجيريا.
The devil is in me, Court.
الشيطان موجود في داخلي، محكمة !.
Court: Sleep.
نامي.
Woman: Have you ever been?
هل كنت هناك في أي وقت مضى؟
Court: Where?
أين؟
Woman: Nigeria.
نيجيريا؟
Court: Never.
أبداً.
My mum wanted to,
أرادت أمي ذلك،
couldn’t afford it.
لم أستطع تحملها.
Woman: Wish I could.
أتمنى لو استطعت.
I have this feeling I’d be happy there.
لدي شعور بأنني سأكون سعيدة هناك.
Why does everyone get rid of me?
لماذا يتخلص مني كل شخص؟
Court: I don't want to get rid of you.
لا أريد التخلص منك.
Woman: You don't need me.
أنت لا تحتاجني.
You’re just too blind to see it now.
أنت فقط أعمى لترى ذلك الآن.
Boy: What do you do all day?
ما الذي تفعله طوال اليوم؟
Marcus: Read.
أقرأ.
Boy: Don't you get bored?
ألا يصيبك الملل؟
And how come you ain't got a job anyway?
ولماذا لم تحصل على عمل حتى الآن بأية حال؟
Marcus: I am retired.
أنا متقاعد.
Boy: So?
إذاً؟
Marcus: So I've done my bit for Queen and country, now I work for myself.
إذاً لقد قمت بواجبي تجاه الملكة وتجاه بلدي، والآن أعمل لنفسي.
Boy: No, now you sit around like a bum all day.
لا، الآن أنت تجلس كالبوم طوال اليوم.
Marcus: Because I do what I like?
لأنني أفعل ما أحبه؟
Boy: Look man, reading don't feed no one.
انظر يا رجل، القراءة لا تشبع أحداً.
And it particularly don't feed your spliff habit.
إنها لا تشبع عادتك في التحشيش بشكل خاص.
Marcus: It feeds my mind and my soul.
إنها تشبع عقلي وروحي.
Boy: Arguing with you is a waste of time, Marcus.
النقاش معك مضيعة للوقت، ماركوس.
Marcus: You’re a rapper, am I right?
أنت مغني راب؟ هل أنا مصيب؟
Boy: Yeah.
نعم.
Marcus: A modern day poet.
شاعر حداثوي.
Boy: Yeah, you could say that.
نعم، يمكنك أن تقول ذلك.
Marcus: So what do you talk about?
إذاً عن ماذا تتحدث؟
Boy: What's that supposed to mean?
ماذا يفترض بذلك أن يعني؟
Marcus: Simple. What do you rap about?
الأمر بسيط. ما الذي يتناوله غناء الراب الذي تقدمه؟
Boy: Reality, man.
الواقع، يا رجل.
Marcus: Whose reality?
واقع من؟
Boy: My fuckin' reality.
واقعي اللعين.
Marcus: Tell me about your reality.
أخبرني عن واقعك.
Boy: Racism, oppression, people like me not getting a break in life.
العنصرية، الاكتئاب، الأشخاص المشابهين لي الذين لم ينالوا فرصتهم في الحياة.
Marcus: So what solutions do you offer? I mean, the job of a poet is not just --
إذاً ما الحلول التي تقدمها؟ أعني، أن وظيفة الشاعر ليست فقط...
Boy: Man, fight the power! Simple: blow the motherfuckers out of the sky.
الإنسان، محاربة القوة. البساطة. تدمير ملعوني الأمهات كلياً.
Marcus: With an AK-47?
ببندقية كلاشينكوف 47؟
Boy: Man, if I had one, too fuckin' right.
يارجل، لو أنني ملكت واحدة، فذلك الشيئ اللعين سيكون صحيحاً جداً.
Marcus: And how many soldiers have you recruited to fight this war with you?
وكم جندي قد جندت ليقاتل في هذه الحرب معك؟
Boy: Oh, Marcus, you know what I mean.
أوه، ماركوس، أنت تعلم ما أقصده.
Marcus: When a man resorts to profanities,
عندما يلجأ الشخص إلى الشتائم،
it’s a sure sign of his inability to express himself.
فإنها علامة أكيدة على عدم قدرته على التعبير عن نفسه.
Boy: See man, you’re just taking the piss out of me now.
انظر يا رجل، أنت فقط تسخر مني الآن.
Marcus: The Panthers.
الفهود.
Boy: Panthers?
الفهود؟
Ass kickin' guys who were fed up with all that white supremacist, powers-that-be bullshit,
الشبان راكلي المؤخرات الذين سئموا من ذلك العنصري الأبيض، أصحاب السلطة، هراء،
and just went in there and kicked everybody's arse.
وفقط دخلوا هناك وركلوا مؤخرة كل شخص.
Fuckin’ wicked, man. I saw the movie. Bad! What?
لعين حقير، يا رجل. رأيت الفيلم. سيئ! ماذا؟
Director 1: I saw his last film.
رأيت فيلمه الأخير.
Épuise, right?
مرهق، صحيح؟
Woman 1: Yes.
نعم.
D1: Not to make a bad joke, but it was really épuisé.
إنه ليس عمل سيئ، لكنه مرهق.
Epuisé -- tired, exhausted, fed up.
مرهق -- متعب، منهك، مضجر.
Director 2: Can you not shut up?
هل بإمكانك ألا تصمت؟
Now, you talk straight to me, what’s wrong with my films?
الآن، أنت تتحدث إلي مباشرة، ما العيب في أفلامي؟
Let’s go.
دعنا نمضي.
W1: They suck.
إنها مقرفة.
Woman 2: They suck? What about yours?
إنها مقرفة؟ ماذا بشأن أفلامك؟
What, what, what, what about, what?
ماذا، ماذا، ماذا، ماذا بشأن، ماذا؟
What do you think about your movie?
ما رأيك بأفلامك؟
D1: My movies, they are OK, fine.
أفلامي، إنها جيدة.
They are better than making documentaries no one ever sees.
إنها أفضل من صناعة أفلام وثائقية لا أحد يراها أبداً.
What the fuck are you talking about?
ما هذا الهراء الذي تتكلم عنه؟
Did you ever move your fuckin' ass from Hollywood
هل حدث أن انتقلت من هوليود
to go and film something real?
لتذهب وتصنع فيلماً عن شيئ ما حقيقي؟
You make people fuckin' sleep.
أنت تجعل الناس ينامون اللعنة.
Dream about bullshit.
يحلمون بالهراء
(Applause)
تصفيق
Newton Aduaka: Thank you. The first clip, really, is
نيوتن أدوكا: شكراً لكم. أنا قمت فقط -- بالمقطع الأول حقيقة، من هذه المقاطع
totally trying to capture what cinema is for me,
حقيقة تحاول جميع المقاطع أن تجذب الانتباه إلى ما هي السينما بالنسبة لي،
and where I'm coming from in terms of cinema.
ومن أين أتيت بالمعنى السينمائي.
The first piece was, really, there's a young woman talking about Nigeria,
كان الجزءالأول، حقيقة، هناك امرأة شابة تتحدث عن نيجيريا،
that she has a feeling she'll be happy there.
إذ لديها إحساس بأنها ستكون سعيدة هناك.
These are the sentiments of someone that's been away from home.
هذه هي مشاعر أي شخص بقي بعيداً عن وطنه
And that was something that I went through, you know, and I'm still going through.
وهو شيئ مررت به، أتعلمون، ولازلت أمر به.
I've not been home for quite a while, for about five years now.
لم أكن في وطني حتى الآن لفترة من الزمن، لحوالي خمس سنوات من الآن.
I've been away 20 years in total.
لقد بقيت بعيدأ عن الوطن حتى الآن لمدة عشرين سنة بالمجمل.
And so it’s really --
وهكذا فإنه شعور حقيقي--
it's really how suddenly, you know, this was made in 1997,
إنه حقاً وكيف وبشكل مفاجئ، تعلمون، صنع هذا الفيلم في 1997،
which is the time of Abacha -- the military dictatorship,
وهي فترة الأباتشا، الدكتاتورية العسكرية،
the worst part of Nigerian history, this post-colonial history.
أسوأ فترة في تاريخ نيجيريا، تاريخ ما بعد الاستعمار.
So, for this girl to have these dreams
وهكذا، فإن وجود هذه الأحلام لدى هذه الفتاة،
is simply how we preserve a sense of what home is.
هو ببساطة يشير إلى الطريقة التي نحتفظ بها بمعنى حول ماهية الوطن.
How -- and it's sort of, perhaps romantic, but I think beautiful,
كيف-- وهو نوعاً ما، ربما رومانسي، لكني أعتقد أنه جميل.
because you just need something to hold on to,
لأنك فقط تحتاج إلى شيئ ما تتمسك به،
especially in a society where you feel alienated.
خصوصاً في مجتمع تشعر فيه بأنك غير مرغوب.
Which takes us to the next piece, where the young man
الأمر الذي يأخذنا إلى الجزء الثاني، حيث الرجل الفتي
talks about lack of opportunity: living as a black person in Europe,
يتحدث عن فقدان الفرصة، العيش كشخص أسود في أوروبا.
the glass ceiling that we all know about, that we all talk about,
السقف الزجاجي الذي نعلم جميعنا بشأنه، والذي نتحدث جميعنا عنه، تعلمون.
and his reality.
والقدوم -- تعلمون، وواقعه.
Again, this was my -- this was me talking about --
مرة ثانية، كان هذا -- كان هذا كلامي عن --
this was, again, the time of multiculturalism in the United Kingdom,
كان هذا، ثانية، وقت التعددية الثقافية في المملكة المتحدة،
and there was this buzzword -- and it was trying to say,
وكانت هناك هذه الكلمة الطنانة وكانت حقيقة، بالنسبة لي، تحاول أن تقول،
what exactly does this multiculturalism mean in the real lives of people?
ما الذي تعنيه كلمة التعددية الثقافية بالضبط في حياة الناس الحقيقية؟
And what would a child --
وماذا طفل،
what does a child like Jamie -- the young boy -- think,
ماذا طفل مثل جيمي، الفتي، يفكر،
I mean, with all this anger that's built up inside of him?
أعني، مع كل هذا الغضب الذي تراكم داخله،
What happens with that?
وماذا -- يحدث بوجود ذلك الغضب؟
What, of course, happens with that is violence,
الذي، بالطبع، يحدث مع ذلك الغضب هو العنف، الذي --
which we see when we talk about the ghettos
الذي نراه عندما، تعلمون، نتحدث عن الأقليات
and we talk about, you know, South Central L.A. and this kind of stuff,
ونحن نتحدث عن، تعلمون، وسط وإلى جنوب لوس انجلوس. و هذا النوع من العنف.
and which eventually, when channeled, becomes,
الذي أخيراً وفي بعض الأحيان عندما يوجه يصبح،
you know, evolves and manifests itself as riots --
تعلمون، يتطور ويظهر نفسه كأعمال شغب،
like the one in France two years ago, where I live,
مثل تلك التي حدثت في فرنسا منذ سنتين، حيث أعيش،
which shocked everybody, because everyone thought, "Oh well,
والتي صدمت الجميع، لأن الجميع اعتقد، " أوه حسن،
France is a liberal society."
فرنسا مجتمع ليبرالي."
But I lived in England for 18 years.
لكنني عشت في انكلترا لمدة 18 عاما،
I've lived in France for about four, and I feel actually
وقد عشت في فرنسا حتى الآن حوالي أربعة أعوام، وأشعر حقيقة
thrown back 20 years, living in France.
وكأنني أعيش فترة ما قبل عشرين سنة في فرنسا.
And then, the third piece. The third piece for me is the question:
ومن ثم الجزء الثالث. الجزء الثالث بالنسبة لي هو السؤال:
What is cinema to you? What do you do with cinema?
ما هي السينما بالنسبة لك، ما الذي تفعله بالسينما؟
There's a young director, Hollywood director, with his friends --
هناك شاب -- المخرج، مخرج هوليود، مع أصدقائه،
fellow filmmakers -- talking about what cinema means.
صانعوا أفلام زملاء، يتحدثون عن ما تعنيه السينما.
I suppose that will take me to my last piece --
وأعتقد أن ذلك سيأخذنا إلى فيلمي الأخير،
what cinema means for me.
ما الذي تعنيه السينما بالنسبة لي.
My life started as a -- I started life in 1966,
بدأت حياتي كـ -- بدأت الحياة في 1966،
a few months before the Biafran, which lasted for three years
شهور قليلة قبل الحرب الأهلية النيجيرية التي استمرت لثلاث سنوات،
and it was three years of war.
وكانت ثلاث سنوات من الحرب.
So that whole thing,
إذا ذلك هو الأمر برمته،
that whole childhood echoes and takes me into the next piece.
تلك الطفولة برمتها يتردد صداها وتأخذني إلى الجزء التالي.
(Video) Voice: Onicha, off to school with your brother.
فيديو: أونيتشا، اذهبي إلى المدرسة مع أخيك.
Onicha: Yes, mama.
نعم، ماما.
Commander: Soldiers, you are going to fight a battle,
ايها الجنود، ستذهبون للقتال في المعركة،
so you must get ready and willing to die.
إذا يجب أن تكونوا جاهزين ومستعدين للموت.
You must get -- ?
يجب أن تكونوا؟
Child Soldiers: Ready and willing to die.
جاهزين ومستعدين للموت.
C: Success, the change is only coming through the barrel of the gun.
النجاح، يأتي التغيير فقط عن طريق فوهة البندقية.
CS: The barrel of the gun!
فوهة البندقية.
C: This is the gun.
هذه هي البندقية.
C: This is an AK-47 rifle. This is your life.
هذه بندقية الكلاشينكوف 47، هذه هي حياتكم.
This is your life. This is ... this is ... this is your life.
هذه هي حياتكم. هذه هي.... هذه هي حياتكم.
Ezra: They give us the special drugs. We call it bubbles.
إنهم يعطوننا عقاقير خاصة. نحن ندعوها فقاعات.
Amphetamines.
الأمفيتامينات.
Soldiers: Rain come, sun come, soldier man dey go.
يأتي المطر، تأتي الشمس، يذهب الجندي.
We went from one village to another -- three villages.
لقد غادرنا من قرية لأخرى -- ثلاث قرى.
I don’t remember how we got there.
لا أذكر كيف وصلنا هناك.
Witness: We walked and walked for two days.
مشينا ومشينا ليومين.
We didn't eat.
لم نأكل.
There was no food, just little rice.
لم يكن هناك طعام، فقط القليل من الأرز.
Without food -- I was sick.
من دون الطعام كنت مريضة.
The injection made us not to have mind.
جعلتنا الحقن نفقد عقلنا.
God will forgive us.
سيسامحنا الرب.
He knows we did not know. We did not know!
هو يعلم أننا لم نكن نعرف. لم نكن نعرف!
Committee Chairman: Do you remember January 6th, 1999?
هل تذكر السادس من كانون الثاني، 1999؟
Ezra: I don’t remember.
لا أذكر.
Various Voices: You will die! You will die! (Screaming)
ستموت! ستموت! (صراخ)
Onicha: Ezra! (Ezra: Onicha! Onicha!)
أونيتشا: عزرا! (عزرا: أونيتشا! أونيتشا!)
Various Voices: ♫ We don't need no more trouble ♫
لا نحتاج لا مزيد من المشاكل
♫ No more trouble ♫
لا مزيد من المشاكل
They killed my mother.
لقد قتلوا أمي.
The Mende sons of bastards.
الأوغاد من أبناء المنديين.
(Shouting)
(صراخ)
Who is she?
من هي؟
Me.
أنا.
Why you giving these to me?
لماذا تعطيني هذه لي؟
So you can stop staring at me.
هكذا يمكنك التوقف عن التحديق بي.
My story is a little bit complicated.
قصتي معقدة قليلاً.
I’m interested.
أنا مستمتع.
Mariam is pregnant.
مريم حامل.
You know what you are? A crocodile.
هل تعلم ما أنت؟ تمساح.
Big mouth. Short legs.
فم كبير. أرجل قصيرة.
In front of Rufus you are Ezra the coward.
أمام روفوز أنت عزرا الجبان.
He’s not taking care of his troops.
إنه لا يعتني بجنوده.
Troop, pay your last honor. Salute.
أيها الجنود، عبروا عن احترامكم. حيّوا.
Open your eyes, Ezra.
افتح عينيك، عزرا.
A blind man can see that the diamonds end up in his pocket.
يمكن للرجل الأعمى أن يرى أن الماس ينتهي في جيبه.
♫ We don't need no more trouble ♫
لا نحتاج لا مزيد من المشاكل
Get that idiot out!
اطرد ذلك الغبي!
I take you are preparing a major attack?
أتقبل أنك تحضر لهجوم رئيسي؟
This must be the mine.
هذا الهجوم يجب ان يكون هجومي.
Your girl is here.
ابنتك هنا.
Well done, well done.
حسناً فعلت، حسناً فعلت.
That is what you are here for, no?
ذلك ما أنت هنا من أجله، لا؟
You are planning to go back to fight are you?
أنت تخطط للعودة للقتال أليس كذلك؟
♫ We don't need no more trouble ♫
♫لا نحتاج لا مزيد من المشاكل♫
♫ No more trouble ♫
♫لا مزيد من المشاكل♫
Wake up! Everybody wake up. Road block!
استيقظ! الجميع استيقظوا. الطريق مغلق!
♫ We don't need no more ... ♫
♫لا نحتاج لا مزيد...♫
Committee Chairman: We hope that, with your help and the help of others, that this commission
نأمل أنه ، بمساعدتك ومساعدة الآخرين، هذه اللجنة
will go a long way towards understanding the causes of the rebel war.
ستقطع شوطاً بعيداً باتجاه فهم أسباب حرب المتمردين.
More than that, begin a healing process and finally to --
وأكثر من ذلك، بدء عملية الشفاء وأخيراً إلى --
as an act of closure to a terrible period in this country’s history.
كعمل من أعمال إنهاء الفترة المريعة في تاريخ هذه البلدة.
The beginning of hope.
بداية الأمل.
Mr. Ezra Gelehun, please stand.
سيد عزرا، قف من فضلك.
State your name and age for the commission.
صرّح عن اسمك وعمرك للجنة.
Ezra: My name is Ezra Gelehun.
اسمي عزرا غيلهون.
I am 15 or 16. I don’t remember.
أنا في الخامسة عشر أو السادسة عشر. لا أذكر.
Ask my sister, she is the witch, she knows everything.
اسألوا أختي، إنها عرافة، إنها تعرف كل شيئ.
(Sister: 16.)
16.
CC: Mr. Gelehun, I’d like to remind you you’re not on trial here
سيد غيلهون، أرغب أن أذكرك بأنك لست في محاكمة هنا
for any crimes you committed.
من أجل أي من الجرائم التي ارتكبتها.
E: We were fighting for our freedom.
كنا نقاتل من أجل حريتنا.
If killing in a war is a crime,
إذا كان القتل في الحرب جريمة،
then you have to charge every soldier in the world.
إذاً عليك أن تتهم كل جندي في العالم.
War is a crime, yes, but I did not start it.
الحرب هي جريمة، نعم، لكنني لم أبدأها.
You too are a retired General, not so?
أنت أيضاً متقاعد يا جنرال، ألست كذلك؟
CC: Yes, correct.
نعم، صحيح.
E: So you too must stand trial then.
إذاً أنت أيضاً يجب أن تخضع للمحاكمة بعد ذلك.
Our government was corrupt.
حكومتنا كانت فاسدة.
Lack of education was their way to control power.
نقص التعليم كان طريقتهم لإحكام السيطرة.
If I may ask, do you pay for school in your country?
إذا كان لي أن أسأل، هل تدفعون للمدرسة في بلدكم؟
CC: No, we don’t.
لا، نحن لا ندفع.
E: You are richer than us.
أنتم أغنى منا.
But we pay for school.
لكننا ندفع للمدرسة.
Your country talks about democracy,
بلدكم تتحدث عن الديموقراطية،
but you support corrupt governments like my own.
لكنكم تدعمون الحكومات الفاسدة كحكومتي.
Why? Because you want our diamond.
لماذا؟ لأنكم تريدون ماسنا.
Ask if anyone in this room have ever seen real diamond before?
اسأل أي شخص في هذه الغرفة ما إذا سبق له أن رأى الماس الحقيقي من قبل؟
No.
لا.
CC: Mr. Gelehun, I'd like to remind you, you're not on trial here today.
سيد غيلهون، أرغب أن أذكرك، أنت لست في محاكمة هنا اليوم.
You are not on trial.
أنت لست في محاكمة.
E: Then let me go.
إذاً دعني أذهب.
CC: I can't do that, son.
لا أستطيع فعل ذلك، بني.
E: So you are a liar.
إذاً أنت كاذب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
NA: Thank you. Just very quickly to say that my point really here,
نيوتن أدوكا: شكراً. فقط وبسرعة شديدة أريد أن أقول أن غايتي هنا،
is that while we’re making all these huge advancements,
هو أنه بينما نصنع كل تلك التقدمات الهائلة،
what we're doing, which for me, you know, I think we should --
إن ما نفعله، الذي بالنسبة لي، تعلمون، أعتقد أنه علينا --
Africa should move forward, but we should remember,
إفريقيا يجب ان تتقدم للأمام، لكن علينا أن نتذكر،
so we do not go back here again.
إذاً ألا نعود إلى هنا مجدداً.
Thank you.
شكرا.
Emeka Okafor: Thank you, Newton.
إيميكا أوكافور: شكراً، نيوتن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
One of the themes that comes through very strongly
واحد من المواضيع التي تجلت بقوة
in the piece we just watched is this sense of the psychological trauma of the young
في الجزء الذي شاهدناه للتو هو الإحساس بالصدمة النفسية لدى الفتى
that have to play this role of being child soldiers.
الذي عليه أن يلعب هذا الدور لطفل -- أن يكونوا جنوداً أطفالاً.
And considering where you are coming from,
وبالأخذ بعين الاعتبار المكان الذي أتيت منه،
and when we consider the extent to which it’s not taken as seriously
وعندما نأخذ بعين الاعتبار إلى أي مدى لم يؤخذ هذا الموضوع بجدية
as it should be, what would you have to say about that?
كما هو مفترض، ماذا لديك لتقوله عن هذا الموضوع؟
NA: In the process of my research, I actually spent
نيوتن أدوكا: في عملية بحثي، ذهبت -- حقيقة أمضيت
a bit of time in Sierra Leone researching this.
وقتاً قصيراً في سييرا ليون أعيد بحث هذا الموضوع.
And I remember I met a lot of child soldiers --
وقابلت -- أذكر أنني قابلت الكثير من الجنود الأطفال،
ex-combatants, as they like to be called.
المقاتلين السابقين، كما يحبون أن يدعون.
I met psychosocial workers who worked with them.
قابلت العاملين الاجتماعيين الذين عملوا معهم.
I met psychiatrists who spent time with them,
قابلت الأطباء النفسيين الذين أمضوا الوقت معهم،
aid workers, NGOs, the whole lot.
عمال الإغاثة، المنظمات غير الحكومية، الكثير.
But I remember on the flight back on my last trip,
لكنني أذكر أنني على متن رحلة العودة بالطائرة في رحلتي الأخيرة،
I remember breaking down in tears and thinking to myself,
أذكر أنني أجهشت بالبكاء والتفكير لنفسي،
if any kid in the West, in the western world,
لو أن هؤلاء الأطفال، لو أن أي طفل في الغرب، في العالم الغربي،
went through a day of what any of those kids have gone through,
مر خلال يوم بما مر به أي من هؤلاء الأطفال،
they will be in therapy for the rest of their natural lives.
فإنهم سيخضعون للعلاج لبقية حياتهم الطبيعية.
So for me, the thought that we have all these children --
لذا بالنسبة لي، فكرة أنه لدينا كل هؤلاء الأطفال،
it’s a generation, we have a whole generation of children --
إنهم جيل، لدينا جيل كامل من الأطفال
who have been put through so much psychological trauma or damage,
الذين قد تعرضوا وحتى الآن للكثير من الشدات النفسية أو الضرر النفسي،
and Africa has to live with that.
وعلى إفريقيا أن تتعايش مع ذلك.
But I’m just saying to factor that in,
لكنني فقط أشير إلى أخذ ذلك بعين الاعتبار،
factor that in with all this great advancement,
أخذ ذلك بعين الاعتبار مع كل هذا التقدم العظيم،
all this pronouncement of great achievement.
ومع كل هذه التصريحات عن الإنجاز العظيم.
That’s really my thinking.
هذا حقيقة تفكيري.
EO: Well, we thank you again for coming to the TED stage.
إيميكا أوكافور: حسن، نشكرك ثانية لقدومك إلى مسرح تيد.
That was a very moving piece.
كان ذلك جزءاً مؤثراً.
NA: Thank you.
نيوتن أدوكا: شكرا لك.
EO: Thank you.
إيميكا أوكافور: شكرا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)